So we start today. Today's דף daf is ל"ו, Lamed Vav, and
we start at the very bottom of ל"ה עמוד ב', Lamed He
Amud Bet,
and we are in the middle of discussing רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's
position, excuse me, רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's position in the משנה Mishna
that says that the act of שחיטה shechita makes the meat הוכשר,
huchshar, susceptible for טומאה, tumah, and you don't need the blood. And
the question in the גמרא Gemara right now is as to whether
he would—what is his position about the blood of שחיטה? shechita? Is
it that you don't need it or that he would say the
blood of שחיטה shechita does not actually create—is not actually מכשיר, machshir,
does not make food susceptible, other types of food? And we went
back and forth yesterday and we are basically had set out there
that—that it's taken for granted that the blood of a corpse, of
a slain person is מכשיר, machshir,
things that are according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, slight variations of
that, either naturally a person who died naturally, so it's a dead
person but not slain, or a wound, an injury but not—but not
killing a person, that is not מכשיר. machshir. A slain person is.
And the question is, okay, but what about the blood of שחיטה?
shechita? What's the story with that? And that was not resolved. So
we are now going to look at what is the source to
assume that the blood of a slain person is מכשיר machshir and
the blood of שחיטה shechita is מכשיר. machshir. So let's take a
look. We start with four lines from the bottom, second word on
the line. ומאי שנא דם חללים דמכשיר, U'mai shna dam chalalim d'machshir,
why are we taking it for granted that blood of a slain
person is מכשיר? machshir? דכתיב, Dich'tiv, because the verse says, ודם חללים
ישתה, V'dam chalalim yishteh, it says in a poetic way about a
pretty gruesome thing, it says 'the blood of corpses he will drink.'
So it refers to blood as something that is drunk and therefore
something that is a type of a liquid, and has the same
effect as water, which is
to—which—which is to מכשיר, machshir, to make food susceptible for טומאה. tumah.
So why are we taking that for granted and that everybody agrees?
דם שחיטה נמי כתיב, Dam shechita nami ktiv, we have an equal
verse by שחיטה, shechita, it says, על הארץ תשפכנו כמים, Al aretz
tishpachenu kamayim, spill the blood when you slaughter an animal like water.
So you see it should be treated like water. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, ההוא משום דם דפסולי מוקדשים בהנאה דאתא. hahu mishum
dam d'psulei mukdashim behana'ah d'ata.
That is coming not to say any law about being מכשיר, machshir,
that is coming to say that the blood of sacrifices—of things that
were sacrifices but had become invalid, had a blemish and then they
were redeemed, that when you actually slaughter them, their blood, you can
derive benefit from. We don't treat it like the blood of actual
sacrifices that you cannot derive benefit from. Remember, חז"ל Chazal understand that
this פסוק pasuk that says, 'Just like the hart and the deer
you shall slaughter it, spill the blood like water,' it's a little
ambiguous what the context is. חז"ל Chazal understand that the context was
sacrifices that had been blemished and redeemed. So it—it is comparing it
to water to tell you that it is—their blood is permissible in
benefit. Let's take a look now at the top of the next
page. So, top of the next page
of ל"ו עמוד א'. Lamed Vav Amud Alef. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
deitach amina, I might have thought to say, הואיל ואסירי בגיזה ועבודה,
ho'il v'asiri b'giza v'avoda, דמן נמי בעי קבורה, daman nami ba'ei k'vura,
since there are some restrictions that still apply to these פסולי מוקדשים
psulei mukdashim even after you redeem them—what are those restrictions? That you
cannot shear them and you cannot work them—so therefore some of the
remnant of the original sanctity remains, maybe therefore also the blood should
be like the original blood and if it's not used on the
altar it should be buried and you cannot derive any benefit. קמשמע
לן Kamashma lan that no, it's like water, you can derive benefit.
Obviously you can't drink it either because it's still blood, but you
can derive benefit. But it is not to tell you that it's
מכשיר. machshir. Okay, so that verse about blood of שחיטה shechita can
be debated what is it comparing it to water for, but it
is taken for granted that the blood of a slain corpse is
מכשיר machshir and other types of blood not. So I really don't
have a good explanation, it seems pretty arbitrary what the differences are,
but that is what we are saying and now we are going
to look at other exact parameters of what type of blood of
שחיטה shechita and of other things is מכשיר. machshir. So let's take
a look. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, they taught
in the house of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. ודם חללים ישתה, V'dam
chalalim yishteh, 'the blood of corpses or slain' I should say 'slain
people he shall drink.' פרט לדם קילוח שאינו מכשיר את הזרעים. Prat
l'dam kiluach she'eino machshir et hazra'im.
This excludes the blood of squirting, of spurting, which is not מכשיר.
machshir. What does this mean? So when a person or an animal
is cut or is slain,
then the—apparently the blood originally drips out a little bit and then
it comes more gushing out when I—presumably the arteries or whatever, the
veins start pumping, comes gushing out and then at the end goes
back to dripping. So the middle squirting is considered to be when
the... actual the way the גמרא Gemara frames this in כריתות, Krisos,
that is דם שהנשמה יוצא בה. dam she-haneshama yotzei bah. That is
the blood when the soul departs. So either again if you're slaughtering
an animal or a person, when the soul of the animal or
the person is departing, when that blood is coming out, or even
if it's just a wound, then still you know, הדם הוא הנפש.
ha-dam hu ha-nefesh. So blood is considered to be the life force.
But it's considered to be what blood is the life force, that
is the blood at this at the spurting. So it is saying,
let's say you have this case, again I'm going to read this
like תוספות Tosafot that focuses in on the slain people as the
context of these discussions when it doesn't say שחיטה. shechita. So therefore
a person is being slain, and we said only the blood of
a slain person, not the blood of a wound. So now we
are saying even if it's the blood of a slain person, it's
the blood it's not the blood that comes out during the spurting.
Interestingly there you might think why not? That's the life blood. But
no, we are saying it has to be the blood once a
person is already slain. So therefore the blood that comes out during
the spurting is when the person is dying and that blood is
not מכשיר, machshir, only the blood that comes out after that spurting
when the person is already considered to be dead. Okay, so that
is the law for that. Now interestingly for the blood of שחיטה,
shechita, it is the opposite. For the blood of שחיטה shechita based
on another גמרא, Gemara, we say it is only the blood of
the life force and not the blood that comes out after that
blood of of spurting. So it is the exact mirror image. Here
it has to be the blood of a corpse, it has to
be already dead. There it is the blood of the שחיטה shechita
itself during the process of dying. Okay, תנו רבנן. tana rabanan. Yes,
question?
Yes it is, at least for this issue about being מכשיר. machshir.
Okay. In terms of by the way also what is considered what
are you חייב כרת chayav kares for, what type of blood, it
is only the blood of the life force, the blood of the
spurting. תנו רבנן השוחט והתיז דמו על הדלעת. tana rabanan ha-shochet ve-hittiz
damo al ha-dala'at. You're shechting and blood got splattered on a gourd.
So we're not talking about the meat, we're talking about whether the
blood can be מכשיר machshir something else, can be מכשיר machshir a
gourd. So רבי אומר הוכשר, Rabbi omer huchshar, it is מכשיר. machshir.
So that is you know sort of you know what we have
been assuming although we didn't know what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
say. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya but רבי חייא אומר תולין, Rabbi Chiya
omer tulin, it's suspended. We have a doubt whether it is הוכשר
huchshar or not. Now also what תולין tulin means is that if
this gourd is תרומה terumah and somebody touches the gourd after this
after it after this blood hit it, so we would not know
for certain whether the תרומה terumah was טמא tamei or not, whether
the gourd had become a הוכשר. huchshar. Okay, so let's see how
the גמרא Gemara explains this.
אנו אמן נסמוך? anu amman nismoch? I'm sorry. So רבי חייא אומר
תולין. Rabbi Chiya omer tulin. אמר רבי אושעיה. amar Rabbi Oshaya. רבי
אושעיה Rabbi Oshaya said: מאחר שרבי אומר הוכשר, me-ahar she-Rabbi omer huchshar,
given that רבי Rabbi said it is הוכשר, huchshar, רבי חייא אמר
תולין Rabbi Chiya amar tulin and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said it's
a doubt,
אנו אמי נסמוך? anu ammi nismoch? Who should we rely on? Who
should we rule like? So you would think look, you know, two-thirds
of the vote or three-quarters of the vote says it's הוכשר. huchshar.
רבי Rabbi says it's הוכשר, huchshar, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says it's
questionably הוכשר, huchshar, so that's one and a half votes against the
half a vote. But look at how it ends. Nevertheless who should
we rely on? בא ונסמוך על דברי רבי שמעון. bo u-nismoch al
divrei Rabbi Shimon. Let's rely on רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in our
משנה mishna שהיה רבי שמעון אומר שחיטה מכשרת ולא דם. she-hayah Rabbi
Shimon omer shechita machsheret velo dam. Only שחיטה shechita for the שחיטה
shechita itself makes the meat susceptible, is מכשיר, machshir, but the blood
of שחיטה shechita is not. So reading רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in
the משנה mishna not that even שחיטה shechita is מכשיר machshir but
only שחיטה shechita is מכשיר, machshir, the blood of שחיטה shechita is
not. So let's add רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon vote to this and
therefore now it's like you know two against one. רבי Rabbi says
it is הוכשר, huchshar, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya doesn't know, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says it isn't. So we have רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
siding with רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya to assume that maybe it isn't.
So which is a little funny, it would seem like it just
makes it a totally split vote. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does to analyze this. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, so
רב פפא Rav Pappa said: הכל מודים היכא דאיתא לדמא מתחילה ועד
סוף. hakol modin heicha de-isso le-dam mi-tchila ve-ad sof. Everybody agrees that
if the blood was spurting from the beginning till the end, now
we're now going to bracket the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon part of
this, just look at the debate of רבי Rabbi and רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya where רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya isn't sure but רבי Rabbi
but רבי Rabbi is sure. So he says the following. Everybody agrees
that if the blood was spurting from the beginning to the end,
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דמכשיר. kulei alma lo pligi de-machshir. Everybody would
agree that it is מכשיר. machshir. כי פליגי ki pligi when did
they debate? בנתקנח הדם בין סימן לסימן. be-nitkane'ach ha-dam bein siman le-siman.
The blood spurted, I'm sorry, I should not have said that, I
missaid it. Not that the blood is spurting from beginning of end
but that the blood that spurted was on the gourd, it spurted
when you started shechting, it was on the gourd and it remained
on the gourd when you finished shechting. Then everybody agrees that it's
הוכשר. huchshar. כי פליגי ki pligi when did they debate? בנתקנח הדם
בין סימן לסימן. be-nitkane'ach ha-dam bein siman le-siman.
It spurted on the gourd, it was quickly wiped off, and then
you finished shechting. So, pretty amazing, since שחטינג shechting normally takes less
than a second, but okay, we'll assume that you paused a little
bit but not enough that it was שהייה, shehiya, so it spurted
on the gourd, it was wiped off and then you finished שחטינג.
shechting. So what's the debate? Here's the debate. רבי סבר Rabbi savar
יש לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, yesh lishchita mitichila v'ad sof, שחיטה, shechita,
the שחיטה shechita process starts from the very beginning to the end.
Remember that debate? That's a fun debate that the גמרא'ס Gemara's always
going to come back to. So שחיטה shechita starts from the very
beginning. והאי דם שחיטה הוא, V'hai dam shechita hu, so the blood
that came out at the first סימן siman is the blood of
שחיטה shechita and therefore it is הוכשר. huchshar. רבי חייא סבר, Rabbi
Chiya savar, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya holds it's true that blood of
שחיטה shechita is מכשיר, machshir, that I'll grant you, but nevertheless אין
לשחיטה אלא בסוף, ein lishchita ela b'sof, שחיטה shechita only is at
the end. והאי דם מכה הוא, V'hai dam maka hu, and this
is blood of a מכה maka because at the time you had
just begun the process, you had not yet done a שחיטה. shechita.
And therefore it is not מכשיר. machshir. However, what happens if you
actually finished the שחיטה shechita and it's there at the end? So
if you finished the שחיטה shechita and it's there at the end,
then by the time the שחיטה'ס shechita's over, now you see that
you actually had done a שחיטה shechita and it is blood of
שחיטה shechita and it is מכשיר. machshir. Now this is actually quite
important in order to understand the debate of יש לשחיטה מתחילה ועד
סוף, yesh lishchita mitichila v'ad sof, because if you remember at the
time we really struggled, we said look, if you want to say
are you doing a process of שחיטה, shechita, of course you're doing
a process of שחיטה shechita from the beginning. If you want to
say when did the שחיטה shechita complete, of course it completed at
the end. So what exactly is the debate? So here it's very
interesting. Here it seems like everybody agrees that when the שחיטה shechita
is over, in retrospect we say, yes, now I see that you
were doing a process of שחיטה. shechita. So if the blood remained
on there by the time the שחיטה shechita was finished, even though
it spurted in the middle, I would say, ah, now the שחיטה'ס
shechita's over, now I'm prepared to call it blood of שחיטה, shechita,
because now I'm prepared to call the process שחיטה. shechita. But I'm
only going to call the process שחיטה shechita from this point forward.
I'm not going to call it retroactively שחיטה. shechita. So it's a
little bizarre. Starting in this point in time, I will say that
anything that happened in the past was שחיטה. shechita. So if the
blood is still on there now, I'll call it blood of שחיטה.
shechita. It was wiped off, there's no blood there now, it doesn't
matter that I'm calling it blood of שחיטה. shechita. That's if שחיטה'ס
shechita's only at the end. If שחיטה'ס shechita's at the beginning, it
means even during the process I'm calling it שחיטה, shechita, not only
once it's finished. And therefore even if it's wiped off, since it
was there during the process, it's called blood of שחיטה. shechita. So
again, notice it's a little bizarre. It's not like the one that
says it's only at the end says it's only the end part
of the process is called שחיטה. shechita. That one is saying no,
the whole process is called שחיטה, shechita, but I'm only prepared to
call it that once the process is over from that time forward.
Okay, so it's a nice nuance in the debate of יש לשחיטה
מתחילה ועד סוף, yesh lishchita mitichila v'ad sof, which also explains that
why if you say שחיטה'ס shechita's not at the end, why you
didn't make it a טריפה. treifa. Because we're saying yes, yes, at
the end then I'm prepared to say the whole process was a
process of שחיטה. shechita. So that's how we're framing this debate. And
therefore if the blood is there at the end, even if it
spurted in the middle, everybody agrees it's שחיטה shechita blood. If it
was wiped off and you're not prepared to call it שחיטה shechita
until you're done, then it was not שחיטה shechita blood. That's the
debate. Okay, so but everybody agrees blood of שחיטה shechita is מכשיר.
machshir. ומאי תולין, U'mai tolvin, so what does the רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya mean when he says we suspend it? תולין הדבר עד גמר
שחיטה. Tolin hadavar ad gmar shechita. It means not we're in doubt,
it means that if blood spurts on the gourd, we wait to
see if it's there at the end of the שחיטה. shechita. אי
איתא לדם בסוף שחיטה, Ee isa ladam b'sof shechita, if the blood
is there when the שחיטה'ס shechita's over, even though it spurted in
the middle, מכשיר, machshir, then it makes the gourd susceptible. ואי לא,
V'ei lo,
if it was wiped off in the middle, לא מכשיר, lo machshir,
it does not, because we will only call it שחיטה shechita blood
when the process is finished, because then we're prepared to say the
whole process was a שחיטה shechita process. ומאי בוא ונסמוך על דברי
רבי שמעון, U'mai bo v'nismach al divrei Rabbi Shimon, what does it
mean come and rely on רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? How is רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon related to this debate? רבי שמעון לא מכשיר. Rabbi
Shimon lo machshir. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon fundamentally says שחיטה shechita blood
is not מכשיר. machshir. לרבי חייא מכשיר, L'Rabbi Chiya machshir, רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya says it is, it's just a question at what point.
So the גמרא Gemara says that's true, but בנתקנח מיהו אשוו להדדי.
b'nitkaneach mihu ashvu l'hadadi. They nevertheless, although they have very different reasons,
they nevertheless agree that when it was wiped off, it was not
הוכשר. huchshar. Okay, it's sort of like a Supreme Court decision where
judges might vote the same way, but each one is going to
write
a separate decision to explain their reasoning which might be different from
the other person's reasoning. So at least when it's wiped off, they
both agree it's not הוכשר, huchshar, but for very different reasons. מר
לא מכשיר ומר לא מכשיר, Mar lo machshir u'mar lo machshir, each
one says that it's not הוכשר, huchshar, one because fundamentally he rejects
blood of שחיטה'ס shechita's הוכשר huchshar and the other because it came
in the middle and was wiped off. הוי ליה רבי חד, v'havei
lei Rabbi chad, so רבי Rabbi is one opinion that says it
is הוכשר, huchshar, והן דרבי חד במקום שנים, v'hein de'rabbi chad b'makom
shnayim, two beat out one, even though they come from very different
reasons, which is quite fascinating, right? Normally we don't have this. Normally
it's two people with the same reason. but here, as long as
it's the same position, even though a different reason, two beats out
one. And now we understand why it's not one and a half
against one and a half, because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is not
saying I don't know, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is saying if it
was wiped off, it is definitely not הוכשר. huchshar. So in that
type of a case, it's רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon against רבי Rabbi and we say it is not הוכשר.
huchshar. That's one version of the debate.
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, Rav Ashi says, תולין לעולם משמע.
tolin l'olam mashma. No, when it says it's suspended, it doesn't mean
we wait to see until the שחיטה shechitah is done. The phrase
תולין tolin means that the status is always in doubt, so always
in doubt. ונתקנח לרבי חייא ספוקי מספקא ליה. venitkenach l'Rabbi Chiya sfukei
mesafeka lei. So I agree with you the issue is around the
process of שחיטה, shechitah, but רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya doesn't have a
definite ruling, he has a doubtful ruling.
אי ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף או אינה לשחיטה אלא בסוף. ei
yeshna l'shechitah mitchilah v'ad sof o einah l'shechitah ela besof. He doesn't
know whether to consider שחיטה shechitah to be the process from the
beginning to consider it a process of שחיטה shechitah or only at
the end he's prepared to call it a process of שחיטה. shechitah.
ומאי תולין, umai tolin, so therefore if it's wiped off, same scenario
you described, it's wiped off, but what רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is
saying is, I don't know how to rule in this case. I
don't know whether it was called blood of שחיטה shechitah from the
beginning of the process or only at the end and now it's
already wiped off. ומאי תולין, umai tolin, so what does it mean
you suspend it? לא אוכלין ולא שורפין, lo ochlin velo sorfin, you
do what you don't know if there's doubtful טומאה tumah by תרומה.
terumah. You can't eat it because maybe it's טמא. tamei. You can't
burn it, maybe it's טהור. tahor. So you have to just wait
for it to sort of rot and you're not allowed to do
anything with it. Okay, so fine, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya has
a doubt how to rule. ומאי בוא ונסמוך על דברי רבי שמעון?
umai bo venismoch al divrei Rabbi Shimon? So what does it mean
let's rely on רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? How is רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon related to this debate? רבי שמעון לא מכשיר, Rabbi Shimon lo
machshir, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says fundamentally blood of שחיטה shechitah is
not מכשיר. machshir. ולרבי חייא ספקא, ul'Rabbi Chiya safka, רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya has a doubt, and a doubt only in this special case
where it was there and wiped off. גמרא gemara says it's true,
but לעניין שריפה מיושבי להדדי. l'inyan sreifah meyushvei l'hadadi. Here's why it's
not one and a half against one and a half. When it
comes to the question of are we prepared to burn it, this
תרומה terumah gourd that this blood hit and then it touched טומאה,
tumah, there at least they agree. מר לא שרפי ומר לא שרפי.
mar lo sarfei umar lo sarfei. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say
don't burn it definitely, blood of שחיטה shechitah is not מכשיר, machshir,
and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya would say don't burn it because maybe
it's not מכשיר machshir in this particular case where it was wiped
off. So therefore they both agree there are two votes not to
burn it. הוי ליה רבי חד, havei lei Rabbi chad, so רבי
Rabbi is one opinion to say burn it, ואין דבריו של אחד
במקום שנים, ve'ein devarav shel echad bimakom shenayim, and he doesn't beat
out the other two. Okay. והכי קאמר, vehachi ka'amar, and this is
what it means. כגון זאת תולין, kegon zot tolin, תולין, tolin, לא
אוכלין ולא שורפין. lo ochlin velo sorfin. So when it says let's
rely on רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it doesn't mean let's rely on
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to consider it טמא tamei and to burn
it, because that would be then because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya then
would be voting the opposite way. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya isn't prepared
to burn it. It means let's rely on רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
to say that you're not allowed to, I'm sorry, did I say
that wrong? Don't rely on רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to say, I'm
sorry, I said it the wrong way. Don't rely on רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon to say eat it, right? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
say it's not הוכשר huchshar and you could definitely eat it. Then
that would be two against one. No, but at least rely on
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to say don't burn it because רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says don't burn it and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says
don't burn it. So it's two votes not to burn it, so
therefore you're not going to burn it. How about eat it? You're
not going to eat it either, right? Because only רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would say eat it. רבי Rabbi and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
would say don't eat it. They're both concerned, one says it's definitely
טמא, tamei, the other says it might be טמא. tamei. So therefore
in this case, the split vote works out perfectly. It works out
that you exactly have the position of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. Don't
eat it, don't burn it. Okay, so because essentially it's one and
a half to one and a half, we're exactly in that doubtful
situation which gets you רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. Don't eat it and
don't burn it. Okay. That is the question about not only whether
blood of שחיטה shechitah is מכשיר, machshir, but again a fascinating application
of ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshna l'shechitah mitchilah v'ad sof, where
here we find out it means that everybody agrees that the whole
process from the beginning is called a שחיטה shechitah process, but the
question is when are we prepared to call it a שחיטה shechitah
process? Only from the very outset or only once it's complete? Okay,
now we move on. בעי רב שמעון בן לקיש, ba'ei Rav Shimon
ben Lakish, so Rav Shimon Lakish asked the following question, ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish asked the following question: צריד של מנחות. tzarid shel menachot.
You have a clump of grain in your מנחה. minchah. Now, you
have your מנחה minchah flour, you mixed it with oil. So the
oil makes the מנחה minchah flour הוכשר, huchshar, susceptible for טומאה. tumah.
But let's say there's a clump of flour that the oil didn't
get to. That oil is not
הוכשר, huchshar, okay, not that oil, that flour is not הוכשר. huchshar.
Now a טמא tamei person touches it. Will it become טמא? tamei?
Well, on the one hand it hasn't been הוכשר, huchshar, but on
the other hand we have a principle which we mentioned a few
days ago and we're about to mention again called חיבת הקודש. chibat
hakodesh. Something that is an object that's going to be offered on
the מזבח, mizbeach, because of the dearness of... sanctity and we will
see that according to some that's even a biblical concept, because of
the dearness of sanctity it's considered to be fit for, fit and
susceptible for טומאה. tumah. So that's the story with this flour that
has not had oil come to it because it's flour of a
מנחה mincha and of a vessel to be offered as a מנחה,
mincha, and the question will be what is this status of חיבת
הקודש? chibas hakodesh? How much does it make it הוכשר huchshar fit?
Again, I do want to point out that there's a nice analogy
to this idea of חיבת הקודש chibas hakodesh to רבי שמעון'ס Rebbe
Shimon's position that the שחיטה shechita is מכשיר. machshir. You don't always
need water. Sometimes by, as I sort of described it, bringing something
under human control, making it fit in a certain way, transforming it
into food, here transforming it into a sacrifice, bringing it sort of
as a part of human society, is one way of saying it,
that also is מכשיר. machshir. Now the question is what is the
implications of this מכשיר machshir of חיבת הקודש. chibas hakodesh. So let's
take a look. אמר, Amar, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בעי ריש לקיש, Ba'ei Reish Lakish, he asks: תרית שמן המנחה, trit
she'min hamincha, this clump of flour of a מנחה, mincha, מונין בו
ראשון ושני או אין מונין בו ראשון ושני? monin bo rishon v'sheini
o ein monin bo rishon v'sheini? I get if a טמא tamei
person touches it, it becomes invalid. That's the principle of חיבת הקודש,
chibas hakodesh, that it substitutes for הכשר. hechshar. But does it really
fully substitute for הכשר? hechshar? If this was הוכשר, huchshar, then if
a טמא tamei person touched it who is a ראשון, rishon, this
would become a שני. sheini. It could make something else a שלישי,
shelishi, like everything we talked about the last two days. Don't worry,
we're not going to revisit that. However, maybe it's different. Maybe it's
not really הוכשר huchshar like normal טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'tahara. Maybe it
just means that if a טמא tamei person touches it, it becomes
invalid, but it does not become really טמא tamei in order to
pass it on. What is the הלכה? halakha? מונין בו ראשון ושני
או אין מונין בו ראשון ושני? monin bo rishon v'sheini o ein
monin bo rishon v'sheini? כי מהנו חיבת הקודש, Ki mehanu chibas hakodesh,
in what way does this concept of חיבת הקודש, chibas hakodesh, the
dearness of קודש kodesh work? לשווייה גופא גופיה, L'shaveyei gufa gufeih, in
order to make it the itself invalid when a טמא tamei person
touches it. That, yes. אבל למימנייה ביה ראשון ושני לא, Aval l'mimanaya
bei rishon v'sheini lo, but to count different levels of טומאה, tumah,
that not. It doesn't really work as becoming טמא, tamei, it just
works as becoming invalid. או דילמא לא שנא, O dilma lo shana,
or maybe it doesn't matter, it's just as good as liquid and
therefore it becomes טמא tamei and can pass it on. So אמר
רבי אלעזר, amar Rebbe Elazar, so רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar says: תא
שמע, ta shma, come and hear. מכל האוכל אשר יאכל אשר יבוא
עליו מים יטמא. Mi'kol ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo alav mayim yitma.
So this is the verse that speaks about if water comes in
contact with food, the food is susceptible and becomes טמא. tamei. אוכל
הבא במים הוכשר, Ochel haba b'mayim huchshar,
food that comes in contact with water is susceptible. אוכל שאינו בא
במים לא הוכשר, Ochel she'eino ba b'mayim lo huchshar, if it's not
come in contact with water, it's not susceptible. So maybe he's trying
to prove that only water, only liquids make it really susceptible. Everything
else works on a different track. So the גמרא Gemara says: give
me a break. אטו ריש לקיש לית ליה אוכל הבא במים? Atu
Reish Lakish leis lei ochel haba b'mayim? What, do you think ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't know this principle that normally food has to
come into contact with water? ריש לקיש הכי קמיבעיא ליה, Reish Lakish
hachi ka mibaya lei, this is his question: חיבת הקודש כאוכל הבא
במים דמי? chibas hakodesh k'ochel haba b'mayim dami?
That was exactly his question. This concept of the dearness of קודש,
kodesh, does that become like it was הוכשר, huchshar, like it came
in contact with liquid and works exactly along the same track? או
לא, O lo, or is it a different track and allows it
to become invalidated but not to become טמא? tamei? So the גמרא
Gemara says: רבי אלעזר נמי מיתירי דקרא קאמר. Rebbe Elazar nami mi'yitirei
d'kra ka'amar. So you're right, obviously ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, רבי אלעזר
Rebbe Elazar also knew that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish knew of this
principle. But his, the reason he brought this was from the redundancy
of the verse. Why? מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look. כתיב, Ksiv,
the verse already says וכי יותן מים על זרע. v'chi yutan mayim
al zera. If water comes in contact with seeds then it is
susceptible. מכל האוכל אשר יאכל למה לי? Mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel lama
li? Why does it say it again, if food comes in contact
with liquid, if it already said if water comes on seeds? Top
of ל"ו עמוד ב'. lamed vav amud beis. לאו לאתויי חיבת הקודש?
Lav l'asuyei chibas hakodesh?
Is it not coming to say only the only track of real
הכשר hechshar is food with liquid and something else like חיבת הקודש,
chibas hakodesh, that is not the same track, that's on a very
different track. Isn't that what the why the פסוק pasuk repeats it?
So the גמרא Gemara says, not necessarily. לא. Lo. חד בטומאת מת
וחד בטומאת שרץ וצריכי. Chad b'tumas meis v'chad b'tumas sheretz u'tzrichi.
It's talking about two different ways of becoming טמא: tamei: either becoming
טמא tamei because it touches a corpse or becoming טמא tamei because
it touches like a dead
rodent and it needs to tell you both cases. דאי אשמעינן טומאת
מת, Di ashmi'inan tumas meis, if you said that when it's a
corpse it needs the food needs to be הוכשר, huchshar, I would
have said התם הוא דבעי הכשר, hasam hu d'bai hechshar, that's where
the food is susceptible only when it came in contact with liquid.
Why? משום דלא מטמא בעדשה. Mishum d'lo m'tamei be-adasha.
Because maybe the impurity of a מת meis is not as powerful
in a limited way as it is by rodents, because by a
מת meis that only transfers טומאה tumah when you have a כזית.
k'zayis. an olive size of flesh, but by a rodent even the
size of like a lentil bean, even a smaller size, so maybe
that would have been a more powerful טומאה tumah and I might
have thought אימא לא בעי הכשר eima lo bei hachsher by rodents,
maybe
although again the טומאה tumah itself is weaker as we'll see in
a minute, but maybe nevertheless what you need to transfer is less,
the threshold of transferring is less, so the same way you can
have a smaller size of a rodent you also don't need the
recep- the one that is receiving the טומאה tumah to be הוכשר,
huchshar, so it had to tell you even by rodents you need
it, you need the food to have been הוכשר. huchshar. The הא
אשמעינן שרץ ha ashmiman sheretz has just told me that by rodents
you need it to be הוכשר, huchshar, משום דלא מטמא טומאת שבעה
mishum d'lo mitamei tumas shiva because that's a weaker טומאה tumah in
the sense that it's not a seven day טומאה, tumah, it's a
one day טומאה. tumah. אבל מת דמטמא טומאת שבעה, aval meis d'mitamei
tumas shiva, but the טומאה tumah of a corpse which makes the-
something טמא tamei for seven days, אימא לא בעי הכשר, eima lo
bei hachsher, maybe that's more powerful and it will transfer even if
the food has not been הוכשר, huchshar, צריכי, tzerichi, you need both.
Okay, so you needed it to tell me regardless of the טומאה,
tumah, the food needs to be הוכשר, huchshar, and we still don't
know the answer whether חיבת הקודש chibas hakodesh is operating on the
same track or on a different track.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues to try to answer this question.
מתני רב יוסף, masni Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked,
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, meaning he or asked,
he tried to demonstrate an answer from our משנה. Mishnah. What does
our משנה Mishnah say? רבי שמעון אומר הוכשרו בשחיטה, Rabbi Shimon Omer
huchsharu b'shchita, that the meat is הוכשר huchshar through the act of
שחיטה. shechita. So there is a great example, right? There is another
parallel track where it is not through liquid, where according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon something becomes susceptible through a different type of a
thing other than liquid, through שחיטה. shechita. So that maybe is analogous
to חיבת הקודש. chibas hakodesh. And the phrase he uses is הוכשרו,
huchsharu, he uses the same verb, it is הוכשר, huchshar, which suggests
that it is the exact same track as liquid. So let's take
a look. הוכשרו בשחיטה. huchsharu b'shchita. הוכשרו huchsharu is הוכשר, huchshar, ואפילו
לממני בה משום ראשון ושני, v'afilu limni bei mishum rishon v'sheni, even
to count ראשון ושני, rishon v'sheni, even to count levels of טומאה.
tumah.
So you see it really is the same track and it really
is susceptible and it is about טומאה tumah and it is not
just about being invalid. So if that works for שחיטה, shechita, presumably
it should work that way for חיבת הקודש. chibas hakodesh. ואמאי, v'amai,
and why does it work that way? והא לאו אוכל הבא במים
הוא, ve'ha lav ochel ha'ba b'mayim hu, this is not liquid that-
food that came in contact with liquid, so you see that even
when it's not water, it's working on the same track and not
a different track, so אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי
Abaye responded, no maybe that's only Rabbinic. עשו כהכשר מים מדרבנן. asu
k'hachsher mayim mid'rabbanan.
Yes, Rabbinically we treated it as if it came in contact with
liquid, but that does not mean that it biblically would have that
status. Now by the way, it sounds like אביי Abaye might be
saying not only did we treat it like הכשר hachsher in terms
of טומאה, tumah, but maybe רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's entire position that
שחיטה shechita is meaningful is a Rabbinic one and not a Biblical
one. But either way his answer is yes, according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon it works like הכשר hachsher and it works like it
really receives and transfers טומאה, tumah, but maybe that's only Rabbinic. And
our question is at a Biblical level. So אמר רבי זירא, amar
Rabbi Zeira, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said, תא שמע, tasha, I'll
give you another example. We said in the following משנה, Mishnah, הבוצר
לגת, ha'botzer legat, you are collecting olives, harvesting olives and you're gonna
press them and make olive oil. Now as you're collecting them in
the basket, some olive juice runs out of some olives and onto
other olives. Is that מכשיר machshir the other olives? So logically the
answer is no, because remember הכשר hachsher is only when you want
the liquid. Here you do not want the liquid to come out
before you get them to the press because then they will, you
know, get- get dirty and fall through the- through the opening of
the basket, you know, through the sieve of the basket, and you
specifically do not want the liquid now. So logically it should not
be הוכשר. huchshar. However, if the basket is actually like sealed at
the bottom, it's not a wicker basket with holes, but it actually,
you know, is- is- has like some type of a- of a
floor at the bottom where liquid cannot get out, then you would
want perhaps the liquid and then it would be מכשיר. machshir. So
there's a debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beis Hillel u'Beis Shammai
how do we approach it when in this case you don't want
the liquid to come out, but it could easily lead to other
cases or you know be confused with other cases where you would
be okay with the liquid coming out. So let's take a look.
שמאי אומר הוכשר, Shammai Omer huchshar, so שמאי Shammai says it is
הוכשר, huchshar, הלל אומר לא הוכשר, Hillel Omer lo huchshar, it is
not. ושתקו ליה הלל לשמאי, ve'shatku lei Hillel le'Shammai, and הלל Hillel
in the end acceded to שמאי, Shammai, he agreed with שמאי'ס Shammai's
position. So here there's a principle that it is הוכשר huchshar even
though it really should not be because you don't want the liquid.
And even when in really it's not the classic case of liquid
that you want, nevertheless we say when it- we say it's gonna
operate on the same track. Takes a look at what the
גמרא's gemara at the גמרא's gemara answer. אמאי? Amai? So why does
this is does this work like real הכשר? hechsher? לאו אוכל הבא
במים הוא? lav ochel ha'ba b'mayim hu? It's not liquid that come
food that comes in contact with liquid. I mean it is, but
it means it's not the real criteria because it's not liquid that
you want, so you see that even when it's not the classic
case, we treat it like real הכשר. hechsher. So אמר ליה אביי,
amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said back, no, that's maybe
Rabbinic. עשו כהכשר מים מדרבנן. asu k'hechsher mayim mi'drabbanan. That's only Rabbinic.
Now that really is Rabbinic because there it's a debate of a
גזירה, gezeira, of a safeguard against the case when you do want
the liquid, and there, of course, since it's exactly use a case
of liquid, it makes complete sense that at a Rabbinic level, we're
going to treat it like the classic case of liquid and say
it works like הכשר. hechsher. Okay, but that's the answer. That's only
Rabbinic. The same way maybe the שחיטה shechita thing is only Rabbinic
and you cannot prove it for the case of חיבת הקודש chibas
ha'kodesh where we want to know what is the story biblically. So
now it's interesting sort of the little frustrated response that this gets.
So אמר ליה רב יוסף, amar lei Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף
Rav Yosef said back to אביי, Abaye, who is אביי's Abaye רבי
Rebbe actually, אמינא לך אנא הוכשרו בשחיטה. amina lach ana huchsharu b'shechita.
I tried to give you an evidence of where it was הוכשר
בשחיטה, huchshar b'shechita, רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon case. I gave you a
great example where it's not liquid, but it uses the phrase הוכשר.
huchshar. ואת אמר לי עשו כהכשר מים, v'at amar li asu k'hechsher
mayim, and you said to me, no, that's Rabbinic, they made it
like הכשר מים, hechsher mayim, but that's only Rabbinic. ואמר לך רבי
זירא, ve'amar lach Rabbi Zeira, and then רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira gave
you a case about the about the olive, and you said to
him same answer, עשו כהכשר מים, asu k'hechsher mayim, oh no, that's
different, there they made it like water but that's only Rabbinic. So
he says, look, both cases you said that at least Rabbinically they
made it like liquid. So at least apply that answer to ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, רבי שמעון בן לקיש נמי. Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish
nami.
So once you're saying that in those cases, at least say it
by ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish case. עשו כהכשר מים, asu k'hechsher mayim,
say at least at a Rabbinic level for ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
that's at least true that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish asks חיבת הקודש,
chibas ha'kodesh, so at least we do have precedent that when you
have something that's not liquid, at least Rabbinically we treat it like
הכשר, hechsher, so that should be true by חיבת הקודש chibas kodesh
as well that it doesn't just invalidate but it really works like
הכשר hechsher to become טמא. tamei. So so אמר ליה, amar lei,
so אביי Abaye said back, אטו ריש לקיש ליתלוס קמיבעיא ליה? atu
Reish Lakish litlos ka mibaya lei? Said wait a minute, you think
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish question was do we make it suspended, meaning
remember this isn't always the case, but classically if something is only
טמא tamei Rabbinically, תרומה terumah only became טמא tamei Rabbinically, so on
the one hand we're not going to eat it because it is
טמא tamei at a Rabbinic level even though biblically you're supposed to
eat it, but because it's only Rabbinic we're also not going to
burn it because biblically it really is טהור. tahor. So he said,
look, when ריש לקיש Reish Lakish asked about does it become טמא
tamei and does this thing transfer the טומאה tumah onto another object,
he didn't just want to know is it Rabbinically טמא. tamei. If
it were Rabbinically טמא tamei the consequence would be you don't eat
it but you don't burn it. That wasn't his question. That, of
course, that's true, that at a Rabbinic level we consider it טמא
tamei like we see in the case by שחיטה shechita we use
this phrase of הוכשרו, huchsharu, that at least at a Rabbinic level
it is real טמא. tamei. But ליתלוס קמיבעיא ליה? litlos ka mibaya
lei? But his question wasn't to hold it suspended like we would
by Rabbinic טומאה, tumah, כי קמיבעיא ליה, ki ka mibaya lei, his
question was לשרוף. lisrof. Is it biblically טמא tamei will we burn
it? So again, biblically we're going to say in a minute and
elaborate on this, there's a principle of חיבת הקודש, chibas ha'kodesh, so
something like the flour of a מנחה mincha although it's not הוכשר
huchshar when it comes in contact with טומאה tumah it's טמא tamei
and that flour, that you actually would burn because that really is
invalid. But ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish question is at a biblical level
will that flour transfer to let's say another מנחה mincha or something
else it touches to also make the other thing טמא tamei at
a biblical level to burn even the other thing. So is this
principle of חיבת הקודש chibas ha'kodesh just makes the thing itself invalid
or also allow it to become really טמא tamei to transfer it
on. And now the גמרא gemara is going to look at this
concept of and we don't know the answer, but now the גמרא
gemara is going to look at this חיבת הקודש chibas ha'kodesh
that that is actually a biblical concept of a way something becomes
susceptible without liquid. So let's take a look. מכלל, Miklal, says the
גמרא, gemara, from this I can infer דחיבת הקודש דאורייתא, d'chibas ha'kodesh
de'oraisa, that that you're assuming at least אביי Abaye is that the
principle חיבת הקודש chibas ha'kodesh is biblical. מנלן? Minalan? Where do you
know this from? אילימא מדיכתיב, ileima midichsiv, if it's because the verse
says והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא, v'ha'basar asher yiga b'chol tamei,
if meat of a sacrifice touches anything טמא tamei you may not
eat it, right? A verse in the Torah in ויקרא. Vayikra. So
האי בשר דאיתכשר במאי? hai basar de'itkashar b'mai? So why does this
how could this meat become טמא? tamei? What did it come in
contact with? אילימא דאיתכשר בדם, ileima de'itkashar b'dam,
if it became in contact with blood, right? Like our משנה mishnah
speaks about the meat becoming הוכשר בדם. huchshar b'dam. So והאמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, ve'ha'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan, but but we have a teaching, מנלן לדם קדשים שאינו
מכשיר. minalan l'dam kodshim she'eino machshir.
Our משנה mishnah was talking about the blood of חולין, chullin, but
we actually say that even if blood of שחיטה shechita is מכשיר,
machshir, blood of sacrifices is not מכשיר. machshir. How do you know?
שנאמר לא תאכלנו על הארץ תשפכנו כמים, Shene'emar lo tochelenu al ha'aretz
tishpechenu kamayim, that same verse where we learn blood of שחיטה shechita
is מכשיר. machshir. Don't eat the blood, spill it like water. Now
that is a verse of a non-sacrifice, and from there we say
the following: דם הנשפך כמים מכשיר, Dam hanishpach kamayim machshir,
blood that you can let spill like water, that is מכשיר. machshir.
שאינו נשפך כמים, She'eino nishpach kamayim,
blood that you don't let spill like water, blood of sacrifices where
you have to catch the blood, אינו מכשיר, eino machshir, that is
not מכשיר. machshir. So you have meat of a sacrifice. How did
it become הוכשר? huchshar? It couldn't have touched its own blood or
blood of other animals around there, that wouldn't do it, that's sacrificial
blood, that is not מכשיר. machshir. אלא הוכשר במשקי בית מטבחיא, Ela
huchshar bemashkei beit mitbechaya,
maybe it became הוכשר huchshar with the liquids of the slaughterhouse. So
what this is a phrase that the גמרא Gemara uses, you know,
a גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbat and other places, that it refers
to the types of liquids that are around in the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, and there's a principle that those liquids do not become
טמא tamei even if טומאה tumah touches them, and not only that,
they also are not מכשיר. machshir. And that's what the גמרא Gemara
is about to say. והאמר, Veha'amar, I mean literally it means the
liquids of a slaughterhouse, but it really means the liquids in the
Temple. והאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Veha'amar Rebbe Yose bar Rebbe Chanina,
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rebbe Yose bar Chanina says, משקי בית מטבחיא,
mashkei beit mitbechaya, when it comes to these liquids in the Temple,
לא דיין שהן דכיין, lo dayan shehen dachein, it's not enough that
they are pure, meaning this was one of the testimonies, you know,
from the period of עדויות Eduyot that was given by יוסי בן
יועזר Yose ben Yoezer I think if memory serves over in שבת,
Shabbat, it says משקי בית מטבחיא דכיין. mashkei beit mitbechaya dachein. The
liquids of the slaughterhouse are pure, which means which was translated to
mean that liquids in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash do not become
טמא. tamei. And now we're adding to that and saying the following:
it's not enough that they are not, do not become טמא, tamei,
אלא שאין מכשירין, ela she'ein machshirin, they do not, when they come
in contact with other liquid, with other food, they do not make
them susceptible. Now it's a little bit bizarre why just because they're
in the Temple do they prevent things from becoming טמא. tamei. So
תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion and he says, if you take
a look at the תוספות Tosafot אלא שאין מכשירין, ela she'ein machshirin,
תוספות Tosafot says, הוי מצי למימר דהוכשר במים מחוברים וטעמא דרבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא דאמר משקי בית מטבחיא אין מכשירין משום דהוו תלושין וקסבר
תלושין לא מכשיר מדאורייתא. Havi matzi lemeimar dehuchshar bemayim mechubarim veta'ama deRebbe
Yose bar Rebbe Chanina de'amar mashkei beit mitbechaya ein machshirin mishum dehavu
tlushin vekasavar tlushin lo machshir mide'oraita.
So he says it's really the principle that according to him it's
really has very little to do with the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
it really has to do with the liquid. If the liquid is
connected to the ground, meaning like in a lake, in a well,
and so on, that's where it is מכשיר, machshir, but if it
is disconnected from the ground it is not מכשיר. machshir. But for
that and therefore תוספות Tosafot says you could have just as easily
have said, so normally most of the liquids in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash are not connected to the ground, right? They're liquids in
vessels and therefore it's not מכשיר. machshir. So תוספות Tosafot says, well,
we could have made a scenario where it actually was, you know,
in contact with liquid in the ground like it fell in, you
know, the כיור, kiyor, the well in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara is now at least framing. So
alright, so could it not have come in contact? So it would,
blood of sacrifices would not have been מכשיר machshir it, liquids in
the Temple would not have been מכשיר machshir it, so what would
have been מכשיר machshir this meat? וכי תימא תרגמה אדמא, Vekhi teima
targma adama,
maybe this thing that liquids in the Temple aren't מכשיר, machshir, maybe
it only means the blood, like we've already said, sacrificial blood is
not מכשיר. machshir. והא משקי קאמר, Veha mashkei ka'amar,
it's in the plural, the liquids. Okay, so therefore we're talking about
all liquids. So what made this meat susceptible? Not blood, not other
liquids in the Temple. אלא לאו דהוכשר בחיבת הקודש, Ela lav dehuchshar
bechibat hakodesh,
unless the Torah talks about meat of sacrifices becoming טמא, tamei, the
only possibility is there's a principle that things that are sacrifices are
automatically susceptible, חיבת הקודש, chibat hakodesh, the dearness of קודש. kodesh. What?
Maybe this is rainwater?
So that's essentially what the גמרא Gemara is going to answer. So
let's take a look. ודילמא, Vedilma, the גמרא Gemara says how do
you know, maybe כדרב יהודה אמר שמואל, kedrav Yehuda amar Shmuel, like
רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel said, דאמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל, de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, כגון שהיתה לו פרה של
זבחי שלמים, kegon shehayta lo para shel zivchei shelamim,
let's say he had a cow that was going to be as
a שלמים shelamim sacrifice. The reason it gives the example of a
שלמים shelamim is because then the בעלים be'alim are going to eat
the meat and going to get the leather and therefore they have
a vested interest in making it as usable and as high quality
as possible. So what did you do? Right before you brought it
to the Temple, והעבירה בנהר, vehe'evira benahar, you passed it through a
river, a wadi, you got it wet. Okay, you wetted the meat
right beforehand and therefore it's, you know, the whole, it has liquid
dripping from it when you שחט shacht it, because that apparently makes
the leather easier to flay off when it's, when it's moist.
שחטה, shachta, and you slaughtered it, ועדיין משקה טופח עליה, ve'adayin mashka
tofei'ach aleiha, the liquid is still dripping on it. So sort of
like Michael said, okay, it could have come wet some other way.
Now רש"י Rashi by the way says, okay, but the liquid is
on the, is on the leather, not on the skin, not on
the meat. So רש"י Rashi says it fell from the skin to
the meat. תוספות Tosafot says no, not necessarily, because maybe you don't
even want it on the meat and remember it has to be
לרצון leratzon or whatever.
or no actually that wasn't תוספות' Tosfos issue, it was another issue
about whether it was תלושים tlushim or not. Anyway תוספות Tosfos says
that the skin is considered, you know, connected to the meat and
one with the meat. So if it's on the skin, it's like
it's on the meat. So anyway, you can't prove it's the חיבת
הקדש. chibas hakodesh. Maybe the meat somehow came in contact with a
liquid, and not liquid of the Temple, notice that's the point, right?
It's liquid from a river outside the Temple. אלא מסיפא. ella meseifa.
All right, so here's how we know the idea of חיבת הקדש
chibas hakodesh from the end of the verse. After it says if
meat becomes טמא, tamei, here's what the end of the verse says:
והבשר vehabasar
and meat, כל טהור יאכל בשר, kol tahor yochal basar, any pure
person shall eat sacrificial meat. Okay, so it says והבשר vehabasar is
an extra word, right? It could have just said כל טהור יאכל.
kol tahor yochal. So what do you do with this extra word,
"and as for the meat"? So we say in a little sort
of almost ironic Talmudic way, "and the meat," לרבות עצים ולבונה, lerabbos
eitzim ulevona, to include things that aren't even meat, to include that
things that can become טמא tamei even things like that are like
meat, that are things that are offered on the altar, like wood
or like frankincense that is burnt on the altar. The גמרא gemara
says, עצים ולבונה בני אכילה נינהו, eitzim ulevona bnei achila ninhu, wood
and frankincense are not foods, so how can they become טמא? tamei?
So אלא חיבת הקדש מכשר להו ומשוי להו אוכל. ella chibas hakodesh
machshar lehu umashvei lehu ochel. The dearness of קודש kodesh makes them
as if they are הוכשר huchshar or is מכשיר machshir them and
makes them into food. So here is obviously two חידושים. chidushim. It's
not just take raw food and makes it food that can become
טמא, tamei, it takes even something that is not food and makes
it as if it's food. But something here that is going to
be a sacrifice, that is fit for becoming טמא. tamei. Again, this
sort of fits along the lines that it's not because it's somehow
a substitute for liquid, but that this makes it, you know, part
of like a human created type of an object, so something that's
now going to be offered as a sacrifice. הכא נמי חיבת הקדש
מכשרתא. hacha nami chibas hakodesh machsharta. Here too, the dearness of קודש
kodesh is מכשיר, machshir, and again so we see that that is
a biblical principle. But what we haven't answered is the question of
ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. Yes, it's a biblical principle that things that
are going to be offered as sacrifices can become טמא, tamei, even
if they're not food or even if they're not הוכשר. huchshar. But
the question is, at a biblical level, do they just become טמא
tamei and invalid?
Do they just become פסול, pasul, invalid, or do they even become
טמא tamei in order to pass it on? Let's just read the
next two lines from the top of the page to wrap this
up, top of לז ע"א. lamed-zayin amud-alef. מאי? mai? So what is
the story with this חיבת הקדש? chibas hakodesh? כי מהני חיבת הקדש
לפסולי דגופיה, ki mahanei chibas hakodesh lifsulei degufei, does is it just
strong enough to make the actual thing פסול, pasul, invalid, אבל לממני
ביה ראשון ושני לא, aval limmnei beih rishon vesheini lo,
but not to count levels of טומאה, tumah, so it's a different
track from טומאה. tumah. It makes this thing invalid when it touches
something טמא, tamei, but it doesn't actually make it טמא. tamei. או
דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo shena, or maybe there's no difference,
maybe it's the exact same track as הכשר. hechsher. And the גמרא
gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know by חיבת הקדש. chibas hakodesh.
And just to tie it back to our משנה, mishna, what we
also don't know is according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says
that שחיטה shechita does the same thing, is a substitute for הכשר,
hechsher, is that, is that at a biblical level or only at
a rabbinic level? And even if it is at a biblical level,
is it a biblical level to become פסול pasul or is it
at a biblical level even to become טמא? tamei? That we do
not know from the משנה mishna as well, that is the obvious
parallel to this case of חיבת הקדש. chibas hakodesh. So with this
thankfully we are done with issues of טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah and
הכשר זרעים. hechsher zeraim. So טהרת זרעים taharas zeraim we put aside
and with the next משנה mishna we return back to issues of
שחיטה וחולין. shechita vechullin.